Type-safe printf() with the C preprocessor

pecanc

It always annoyed me slightly that even though the intended types of arguments to printf() are known at compile time the format string still has to be runtime interpreted. Also, if you use fixed-width integer types extensively it gets annoying to write PRIu64, PRIi32, etc everywhere. Fortunately with modern C features and some slight (ab)use of the C preprocessor we can do much better.

Let's write a compile-time, type-safe printf() replacement. For fun, let's do it without libc and use only facilities provided by the operating system.

Our strategy is use the preprocessor to rewrite the following

const char *world = "world";
int x = 283;
PutLine(&stdout, "hello ", world, " x: ", x);

into something like

WriteCString(&stdout, "hello ");
WriteCString(&stdout, world);
WriteCString(&stdout, " x: ");
WriteInt(&stdout, x);
WriteCString(&stdout, "\n");

First, let's take care of the actual I/O primitives. We'll define a structure for buffering output:

enum ioerror { IOERR_OK = 0, IOERR_WRITE_FAILED = -1 };
struct iobuf {
	ssize_t cap;
	ssize_t len;
	uint8_t *buf __attribute__((counted_by(cap)));
	int fd;
	enum ioerror err;
};

We need a file descriptor to write to, a buffer to accumulate our formatted output in, and a flag to check for errors. I prefer signed sizes and use the counted_by attribute to enable catching errors with -fsanitize=bounds, and for documentation purposes.

Aside: Portability

For the sake of simplicity we're sticking to just Linux here, but it doesn't require much more code to support other systems. All that has to be done is hide the fd member behind a typedef that expands to int on POSIX and HANDLE on Win32, and then introduce a wrapper function to perform the write via the appropriate OS interface (write() on POSIX or WriteFile() on Win32).

Unfortunately, on most platforms besides Linux and Windows we do have to link to libc, since Linux is unusual in having a stable syscall interface. Other *nix operating systems do not have stable syscall numbers and require you to go through libc. Windows is similar in requiring you to go through the interface exposed in kernel32.dll rather than making raw syscalls, but kernel32.dll is mapped into every process's address space automatically, so you don't have to link against anything extra.

How do we get one of these struct iobuf instances? Well, somewhere in our main() function we can put

uint8_t buf[256];
struct iobuf stdout = {.cap = sizeof(buf), .buf = buf, .fd = 1};

and then pass that to anything that needs to write to stdout.

Now we need a couple of functions to append to our buffer and flush our output to the OS:

void Flush(struct iobuf *io)
{
	const uint8_t *buf = io->buf;
	// partial writes are possible on Linux, where write() succeeds but writes fewer bytes than requested.
	while (io->len > 0) {
		ssize_t written = sys_write(io->fd, buf, io->len);
		if (written < 0) {
			io->err = IOERR_WRITE_FAILED;
			break;
		}
		buf += written;
		io->len -= written;
	}
}

void WriteBytes(struct iobuf *io, ssize_t n, const uint8_t bytes[n])
{
	ssize_t written = 0;
	while (io->err == 0 && written < n) {
		ssize_t free = io->cap - io->len;
		ssize_t z = MIN(free, n);
		__builtin_memcpy(io->buf + io->len, bytes, z);
		written += z;
		io->len += z;
		bytes += z;
		if (z < n) Flush(io);
	}
}

All the WriteBytes() function does is copy to our internal buffer and then flush it to the OS once it fills ups. Flush() is responsible for doing the actual OS write, here done by calling the sys_write() function provided by the nolibc.h header that ships with recent Linux kernels. One complication is that the write() syscall can succeed but write fewer bytes than requested, so we have to call it in a loop until it either fails or writes everything. On Win32, writes either succeed fully or not at all, so one need not worry about partial writes and the Flush() function is much simpler.

The advantage of keeping our error code inside the struct iobuf instead of returning it from Flush() is that we can call WriteBytes() many times and then check the error only once at the end. Note that if an error happens WriteBytes() becomes a no-op, so we effectively fall through to wherever the error is handled.

With our output primitives out of the way we can get to the formatting parts. We need to define a bunch of functions that format the things we care about and call WriteBytes() to store their results in our output buffer.

void WriteInt(struct iobuf *io, int64_t x)
{
	// longest possible int64 decimal representation is 20 characters (-9223372036854775808)
	uint8_t s[20];
	ssize_t i = 20;
	bool neg = x < 0;
	if (neg) x = -x;
	do s[--i] = '0' + x % 10; while (x /= 10);
	if (neg) s[--i] = '-';
	WriteBytes(io, 20 - i, s + i);
}

void WriteUInt(struct iobuf *io, uint64_t x)
{
	// also 20: no sign character but maximum uint64 is one character longer (18446744073709551615)
	uint8_t s[20];
	ssize_t i = 20;
	do s[--i] = '0' + x % 10; while (x /= 10);
	WriteBytes(io, 20 - i, s + i);
}

Integers are very straightforward. We only need two functions, one for signed and one for unsigned, since we can cast any smaller integer to a (u)int64_t without the output changing. Floats are much more challenging, since correctly converting floats to strings that can be parsed back to exactly the same value is a surprisingly complex problem. The most practical option is to existing high-quality float-to-string implementation like ryu or zmij.

Pointers are pretty much the same as integers:

void WritePtr(struct iobuf *io, void *p)
{
	uintptr_t x = (uintptr_t)p;
	uint8_t s[16];
	ssize_t i = 16;
	do s[--i] = (x % 16 < 10 ? '0' + x % 16 : 'a' + x % 16 - 10); while (x /= 16);
	WriteBytes(io, 16 - i, s + i);
}

For strings I like to avoid traditional C-style \0-terminated strings, but we want the convenience of being able to write string literals without explicitly passing their length. Fortunately this is possible with a bit of trickery and a clang extension.

We'll start by defining a struct to hold pointer + length pairs. Later you'll see why we wrap these into a struct rather than passing separate arguments.

struct stringfmt { ssize_t len; uint8_t *ptr __attribute__((counted_by(len))); };

#define $S(n,s) ((struct stringfmt){.len = (n), .ptr = (s)})

We define a helper macro to construct struct stringfmts for readability, and $S is visually a bit evocative of the traditional printf-style %s format specifier. One nice advantage of using structs for wrapping our format options is that designated initializers can be used a bit like keyword arguments, which is much more readable than normal printf specifiers. One can imagine defining a struct for advanced integer formatting options like

struct intfmt {
	int64_t x;
	int32_t width;
	enum { JUSTIFY_RIGHT, JUSTIFY_LEFT } justify;
	bool hex;
	bool force_sign;
	uint8_t pad;
};

#define $I(i,...) ((struct intfmt){.x = (i) __VA_OPT__(,) __VA_ARGS__})

which would allow things like PutLine("x: ", $I(x, .width = 10, .force_sign = true, .pad = '0')). I find this easier than remembering the order of fields in printf("x: %+010" PRIi64 "\n"), and it avoids special cases like the printf * specifier for variable widths. While there's something to be said for compactness, I use the more complex format specifiers rarely enough that I always forget the exact syntax for them.

Returning to strings, we need two functions: one that takes our pointer + length pairs and one that takes a standard const char * string.

void WriteStringFmt(struct iobuf *io, struct stringfmt fmt)
{
	WriteBytes(io, fmt.len, fmt.ptr);
}

void WriteCString(struct iobuf *io, const char *const s __attribute__((pass_dynamic_object_size(2))))
{
	ssize_t len = __builtin_dynamic_object_size(s, 2);
	assert(len > 0);  // fails if we were passed something other than a string literal
	WriteBytes(io, len - 1 /* trim off \0 */, (const uint8_t *)s);
}

The trick is that this uses the clang-specific pass_dynamic_object_size attribute to cause the caller to pass an extra, invisible parameter containing the size of the s argument if it is statically known. This parameter is then retrieved with the __builtin_dynamic_object_size() function. If the size of s can't be determined by the compiler __builtin_dynamic_object_size() returns 0, so we can tell if we were called with a string whose size was not a compile-time constant, which usually means anything that's not a string literal. This is an error on the part of the caller and fails the assert.

(Alternatively, you could just call strlen(), but we're trying to avoid libc and zero-terminated strings as much as possible.)

The _dynamic part means the compiler is allowed to insert a small amount of code to more accurately deduce the size of the object. For example, in a case like the following:

WriteCString(io, a < b ? "ab" : "much longer string");

If we had used __attribute__((pass_object_size(2))) then we would always receive a len of 3, since that is all the compiler is able to prove is always accessible. With pass_dynamic_object_size, this gets rewritten to something like WriteCString(io, a < b ? "…" : "…", a < b ? 3 : 19) instead.

That aside, writing strings just involves shuffling bytes to our output buffer. You can imagine implementing other extensions like minimum width and padding fairly straightforwardly.

With our individual formatting functions out of the way it's time to tie it all together into a nicer API. You could use them as they are and manually make a separate function call for each variable you want to print but we would like to write that part automatically, as in the example at the beginning of the article.

The first step is to use C11's _Generic feature to dispatch to one of our formatting functions based on the type of the argument. This is pretty much just manual function overloading.

void Fail(void);

#define DISPATCH_WRITE(x) \
	_Generic((x), \
		int8_t: WriteInt, \
		uint8_t: WriteUInt, \
		int16_t: WriteInt, \
		uint16_t: WriteUInt, \
		int32_t: WriteInt, \
		uint32_t: WriteUInt, \
		int64_t: WriteInt, \
		uint64_t: WriteUInt, \
		size_t: WriteUInt, \
		ssize_t: WriteInt, \
		/* if you were to implement floats: \
		   float: WriteFloat, \
		   double: WriteDouble, */ \
		char *: WriteCString, \
		const char *: WriteCString, \
		struct stringfmt: WriteStringFmt, \
		default: _Generic((x) - (x), ptrdiff_t: WritePtr, default: Fail) \
	)($_io, (x));

_Generic works by taking an expression and a list of type: replacement pairs. It doesn't evaluate the controlling expression but matches its type against the pairs and replaces itself with the matching replacement expression. I tend to think of it as somewhere between the preprocessor and the compiler. Unlike the preprocessor it can access types, but it's completely eliminated by the time code generation starts. Its main use is for type-generic math so you can write sqrt(2.0f) instead of sqrtf.

The nested _Generic on (x) - (x) is to allow dispatching any pointer (other than the ones explicitly listed above that) to WritePtr(). Though any (non-function) C pointer is implicitly convertible to void *, void * in _Generic only matches actual void pointers. However, the result of subtracting any type of pointer from itself is always a ptrdiff_t, so we can match on that instead rather than requiring the caller to explicitly cast pointers to void *.

One quirk of _Generic is that each replacement expression has to typecheck independently before the _Generic is eliminated. This is why you usually have to write _Generic(x, char *: f_str, float: f_float)(x) instead of _Generic(x, char *: f_str(x), float: f_float(x)). This is also what the default: Fail branch in the nested generic is for, since that branch has to type check even if another branch is already matched by the outer _Generic. We don't need to define the Fail() function anywhere, since we explicitly want a compile error if we ever emit it (which would mean we tried to print something without a formatter).

It's also worth noting that _Generic considers const and non-const pointers to be different types, and one will never match the other.

You may notice the reference to the $_io variable which is not yet defined. We'll get back to that.

Now we need some way to call our DISPATCH_WRITE() macro for each argument to PutLine(). Fortunately, looping with the C preprocessor got a lot easier with the __VA_OPT__() feature in C23.

__VA_OPT__() is legal in the expansion of a variadic macro and expands to its argument if __VA_ARGS__ is of non-zero length, and expands to nothing otherwise. The intended use case is when you have a macro like

#define WARN(msg,...) printf("[WARNING] " msg, __VA_ARGS__)

If WARN() is called with only the first argument it will expand to printf("[WARNING] <message>",), which is a syntax error. With __VA_OPT__() you can write it as

#define WARN(msg,...) printf("[WARNING] " msg __VA_OPT__(,) __VA_ARGS__)

and it will properly include the comma only when necessary.

Previously this could be accomplished with non-standard features like the special behavior of the , ## __VA_ARGS__ sequence in gcc, but __VA_OPT__() is both standardized and more flexible. For instance, you can include other macros in the argument of __VA_OPT__(), which will expand if __VA_OPT__() expands.

You might be able to see how we're going to abuse this to loop over our arguments to PutLine(). __VA_OPT__() seems a lot like the base case of recursion: we can use it to execute another macro if we still have arguments left, and stop iteration otherwise.

The techniques in this section are mainly from these two excellent articles.

When a macro is expanded its expansion is scanned again for macros; however by default preprocessor macros cannot expand recursively. That is, #define f(x) f((x)+1) when called as f(1) expands to f(1+1) and not 1+1+1+…. When a macro is expanded the token corresponding to its name is marked (referred to as "painted blue") and blue tokens are ignored as expansion candidates during re-scan. This includes during any expansions triggered during the re-scan, so this can't be bypassed by e.g.

#define f(x) f_recurse((x)+1)
#define f_recurse(x) f(x)

To get around this we need an extra layer of indirection to prevent the token from being painted blue.

#define EMPTY()
#define DEFER(x) x EMPTY()

If we pass a macro to DEFER() we can prevent it from being painted blue, but then we need a way to force a re-scan.

#define EXPAND(...) __VA_ARGS__

#define f(x) DEFER(f_recurse) () ((x)+1)
#define f_recurse() f

EXPAND(DEFER(f)(1))

One expansion is easy, but with only one layer of EXPAND() it stops there. Fortunately it's not hard to have an exponential number of expansions.

#define EVAL(...)  EVAL1(EVAL1(EVAL1(__VA_ARGS__)))
#define EVAL1(...) EVAL2(EVAL2(EVAL2(__VA_ARGS__)))
#define EVAL2(...) EVAL3(EVAL3(EVAL3(__VA_ARGS__)))
#define EVAL3(...) EVAL4(EVAL4(EVAL4(__VA_ARGS__)))
#define EVAL4(...) EVAL5(EVAL5(EVAL5(__VA_ARGS__)))
#define EVAL5(...) __VA_ARGS__

We can get 365[1] expansions out of 6 lines. This does put a hard limit on the number of arguments to PutLine() we can support, but it's trivial to add more if necessary.

With this, we can build a loop in the C preprocessor:

#define FOREACH(f,...) __VA_OPT__(EVAL(FOREACH_IMPL(f, __VA_ARGS__)))
#define FOREACH_IMPL(f,x,...) f(x) __VA_OPT__(DEFER(FOREACH_RECURSE) () (f, __VA_ARGS__))
#define FOREACH_RECURSE() FOREACH_IMPL

This is admittedly a bit arcane, but now that it's built it's pretty easy to use.

Finally we can glue it all together:

#define PutLine(io,...) do{ struct iobuf *$_io = (io); FOREACH(DISPATCH_WRITE, __VA_ARGS__, "\n"); Flush($_io); }while(0)

In case evaluating (io) has side effects we evaluate it once here and stash the results in $_io, which is used in DISPATCH_WRITE().

It should be pretty clear how this works now. We loop through all the arguments of PutLine() (except the iobuf) using our preprocessor metaprogramming and for each of them use _Generic to dispatch to the correct formatting function for an argument of that type. Those convert their arguments to strings and append to a buffer, which we flush with the appropriate OS function.

Overall, this isn't a lot of code for an arguably nicer API than printf(). glibc printf() alone is over 1500 lines of code[2] and needs special compiler support to issue warnings. musl is much better, but still on the order of ~450 LOC. While our implementation is very barebones, it's easy to extend and can provide options via standard C features like designated initializers rather than the limited printf mini-language. Also, it's easy to add support for your own custom types by implementing a Write* function for them and adding it to the _Generic list.[3]

Should you use this in production? Probably not, given that most people are not quite as fond of grotesque preprocessor macros as I am. It's more just meant to exhibit some modern C features and present a novel use for them. I will say that I do use an implementation very much like this in some of my personal projects where no one else has to see it and I find it very usable and convenient.

Collected code in this article (requires a recent version of clang)

Footnotes:

[1]

Each level EVALn gets called 3n times, plus one for the outermost EVAL(), plus the first expansion for free.

[2]

This doesn't even include float-to-string, which is another 1200+ (though it would bloat ours quite a lot as well).

[3]

I was hoping it might be possible to add new _Generic cases without editing the macro directly by abusing the gcc _Pragma("push_macro") and _Pragma("pop_macro") extensions from inside a helper macro with an API like DEFINE_FORMATTER(type, WriteType), but this is extremely brittle and I can't get it to work in the general case.